<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sabertoaster.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://sabertoaster.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-07-28T18:28:35+00:00</updated><id>https://sabertoaster.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A dedicated life-long learner with a passion for deep learning, artificial intelligence, and neuroscience. </subtitle><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Harvard CS197 AI Research Experiences</title><link href="https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2025/harvard-cs197/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Harvard CS197 AI Research Experiences"/><published>2025-07-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2025/harvard-cs197</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2025/harvard-cs197/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="brief-introduction">Brief introduction</h2> <p>This is a course ran by Harvard, instructed by Professor <a href="https://pranavrajpurkar.com/">Pranav Rajpurkar</a>.</p> <blockquote> <p>Dive into cutting-edge development tools like PyTorch, Lightning, and Hugging Face, and streamline your workflow with VSCode, Git, and Conda. You’ll learn how to harness the power of the cloud with AWS and Colab to train massive deep learning models with lightning-fast GPU acceleration. Plus, you’ll master best practices for managing a large number of experiments with Weights and Biases. And that’s just the beginning! This course will also teach you how to systematically read research papers, generate new ideas, and present them in slides or papers. You’ll even learn valuable project management and team communication techniques used by top AI researchers. Don’t miss out on this opportunity to level up your AI skills.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h2 id="chapter-1--2-introduction-to-ai-and-setting-up-environment">Chapter 1 &amp; 2: Introduction to AI and Setting up environment</h2> <p>Typical, intuitive guides to interact with AI and its research + development. Working environment requires source-code version control (Git), environment control (Conda) and editors (VSCode).</p> <hr/> <h2 id="chapter-3-reading-ai-research-papers"><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1bPhwNdCCKkm1_adD0rx1YV6r2JG98qYmTxutT5gdAdQ/edit?tab=t.0">Chapter 3: Reading AI Research Papers</a></h2> <h3 id="objectives"><u>Objectives</u>:</h3> <ul> <li>Conduct a literature search to identify papers relevant to a topic of interest</li> <li>Read a machine learning research paper and summarize its contributions</li> </ul> <h3 id="chapters-content"><u>Chapter's content</u>:</h3> <p>TLDR: Read wide for learning, read deep for improving.</p> <blockquote> <p>I’m going to break down the process of reading AI research papers into two pieces: reading wide, and reading deep. <em><span style="color:red">When you start learning about a new topic, you typically get more out of reading wide</span></em>: this means navigating through literature reading small amounts of individual research papers. Our goal when reading wide is to build and improve our mental model of a research topic. <em><span style="color:red">Once you have identified key works that you want to understand well in the first step, you will want to read deep</span></em>: here, you are trying to read individual papers in depth. Both reading wide and deep are necessary and complimentary, especially when you’re getting started.</p> </blockquote> <h4 id="read-wide">Read wide:</h4> <p>Paperswithcode (AI/ML) | Google scholar | ACM Digital Lib &gt; Taking notes &gt; Check benchmark with recent submissions &gt; Check SOTA &gt; Check dataset (in any order) &gt; Read em and take notes. <br/> Results: Notes condensed with information, may take up to 2-3 hours doing this.</p> <blockquote> <p>At this point, I find myself particularly intrigued by the SOTA methods: Why are they achieving high performance? According to the review paper, it looks like “training strategies using pre-training” have been an advance. Maybe that’s worth keeping an eye out for!</p> </blockquote> <h4 id="read-deep">Read deep:</h4> <p>TLDR: Take incremental approach.</p> <blockquote> <p>So I would like you to take an incremental approach here. Understand that, in your first pass, you will not understand more than 10% of the research paper. The paper may require us to read another more fundamental paper (which might require reading a third paper and so on; it could be turtles all the way down)! Then, in your second pass, you might understand 20% of the paper. Understanding 100% of a paper might require a significant leap, maybe because it’s poorly written, insufficiently detailed, or simply too technically/mathematically advanced. We thus want to aim to build up to understanding as much of the paper as possible – I’ll bet that 70-80% of the paper is a good target.</p> </blockquote> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/2025/07/harvard-cs197-img-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/2025/07/harvard-cs197-img-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/2025/07/harvard-cs197-img-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/2025/07/harvard-cs197-img.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Define your own highlight strategy, for example:</p> <ul> <li>The <span style="color:yellow">yellow highlights</span> are the problems/challenges</li> <li>The <span style="color:pink">pink highlights</span> are the solutions to the challenges</li> <li>The <span style="color:orange">orange highlights</span> are the main contributions of the work we’re reading.</li> </ul> <h3 id="some-useful-tips"><u>Some useful tips</u>:</h3> <ul> <li> <p>Read deep: do a <a href="http://ccr.sigcomm.org/online/files/p83-keshavA.pdf">three-pass approach</a>. <br/><br/> First, take a quick scan through the title, put some brief thought into it. Read the abstract, introduction, section headings. <strong>Identify the research question, the thematics, the papers’ contribution.</strong> Look through the figures for visual details. Glance through <strong>discussion</strong> if exists. Read the conclusion and see if the research question have been solved (?) <br/><br/> Second, focus on the introduction content, preliminary. Grasp the underlying content in <strong>methodology</strong> section and the <strong>results</strong>. Take notes on key points. Skip math terms if too heavy. The goal is to understand the paper’s content without getting bogged down in details. <br/><br/> This pass is a thorough, line-by-line reading with the aim of understanding every detail and challenging the author’s assumptions and claims. This pass is particularly useful for papers that require a deep understanding or are central. <strong>Re-implement</strong> the paper’s work/ <strong>identify areas for improvement</strong>.</p> </li> <li> <p>Read wide: If <strong>doing a literature review/ search, just do the first pass</strong> then look for referenced sources, mentioned SOTA methods, prominent proposed dataset/ benchmark, …</p> </li> <li> <blockquote> <p>You would have thus created a list of concepts you need to learn about, and the relevant paper for each, if the paper specifies any.</p> </blockquote> </li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="chapter-4-fine-tuning-a-language-model-using-hugging-face">Chapter 4: Fine-tuning a Language Model using Hugging Face</h2> <hr/> <h2 id="chapter-5-fine-tuning-a-vision-transformer-using-lightning">Chapter 5: Fine-tuning a Vision Transformer using Lightning</h2> <hr/> <h2 id="chapter-6--7-solidifying-pytorch-fundamentals">Chapter 6 &amp; 7: Solidifying PyTorch Fundamentals</h2> <hr/> <h2 id="chapter-8--9-organizing-model-training-with-weights--biases-and-hydra">Chapter 8 &amp; 9: Organizing Model Training with Weights &amp; Biases and Hydra</h2> <hr/> <h2 id="chapter-10--11-a-framework-for-generating-research-ideas">Chapter 10 &amp; 11: A Framework for Generating Research Ideas</h2> <hr/> <h2 id="chapter-12--13-structuring-a-research-paper">Chapter 12 &amp; 13: Structuring a Research Paper</h2> <hr/> <h2 id="chapter-14--15-aws-ec2-for-deep-learning-setup-optimization-and-hands-on-training-with-chexzero">Chapter 14 &amp; 15: AWS EC2 for Deep Learning: Setup, Optimization, and Hands-on Training with CheXzero</h2> <hr/> <h2 id="chapter-16--17-fine-tuning-your-stable-diffusion-model">Chapter 16 &amp; 17: Fine-Tuning Your Stable Diffusion Model</h2> <hr/> <h2 id="chapter-18-tips-to-manage-your-time-and-efforts">Chapter 18: Tips to Manage Your Time and Efforts</h2> <hr/> <h2 id="chapter-19-making-progress-and-impact-in-ai-research">Chapter 19: Making Progress and Impact in AI Research</h2> <hr/> <h2 id="chapter-20-tips-for-creating-high-quality-slides">Chapter 20: Tips for Creating High-Quality Slides</h2> <hr/> <h2 id="chapter-21-statistical-testing-to-compare-model-performances">Chapter 21: Statistical Testing to Compare Model Performances</h2> <hr/> <h2 id="exercises">Exercises:</h2> <h3 id="assignments">Assignments:</h3> <p>Assignment 1: The Language of Code <br/> Assignment 2: First Dive in AI <br/> Assignment 3: Torched <br/> Assignment 4: Spark Joy <br/> Assignment 5: Ideation and Organization <br/> Assignment 6: Stable Diffusion and Research Operations</p> <hr/> <h3 id="course-project">Course Project:</h3> <p>[Redacted]</p> <hr/> <h2 id="references">References:</h2> <p><br/> <a href="https://www.cs197.seas.harvard.edu/">Course Homepage</a> <br/> <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1uvAbEhbgS_M-uDMTzmOWRlYxqCkogKRXdbKYYT98ooc/edit?tab=t.0#heading=h.act903jwq03w">Docs Content</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Notes and commentaries]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Downfall don’t fall down.</title><link href="https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2025/downfall/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Downfall don’t fall down."/><published>2025-01-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2025/downfall</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2025/downfall/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="preamble">Preamble</h1> <p>The dormitory room reeked of stale air and neglect. Empty takeout containers formed a graveyard across his desk, their contents fossilized into unrecognizable shapes that caught the mild glow of his laptop screen. The boy—twenty but wearing the face of someone much older—sat hunched over his keyboard, fingers dancing across keys with the practiced precision of an addict feeding his habit.</p> <p>2:47 AM. The numbers burned red in the corner of his vision, but time had lost all meaning hours ago. Outside his window, the campus lay dormant, but inside this cramped sanctuary, he was wide awake, pupils dilated from the synthetic euphoria coursing through his veins.</p> <p>The small glass vial sat empty beside his mouse pad, its contents already absorbed into his bloodstream. <strong>Mortis</strong>, they called it on the forums. The temporary death. The ultimate escape from consciousness, from responsibility, from the gnawing awareness of his own mediocrity.</p> <hr/> <p>His roommate had moved out three weeks ago—something about “toxic energy” and “impossible to live with.” Good riddance. Now he had the entire space to himself, free to indulge without judgment, without interruption.</p> <p>The familiar warmth began spreading through his chest, that telltale sign that the Mortis was taking hold. His heartbeat slowed to a hypnotic rhythm, each pulse echoing in his ears like a countdown. The screen before him blurred, the endless scroll of content becoming a meaningless river of light and shadow.</p> <p><em><span style="color:red">“You’re better than this,”</span></em> he whispered to himself, the words tasting like ash. It was a lie he’d stopped believing months ago, but the ritual persisted—a final prayer before the chemical crucifixion.</p> <p>His breathing grew shallow. The euphoria hit like a tidal wave, washing away every sharp edge of reality. The disappointment from his failed group project, the humiliation of being cast out by people he’d thought were friends, the crushing weight of unrealized potential—all of it dissolved in the chemical bliss.</p> <p><em><span style="color:red">They didn’t deserve me anyway,</span></em> he thought as consciousness began to ebb. <em><span style="color:red">Unambitious. Weak. They couldn’t handle someone with real vision.</span></em></p> <p>But even as the lie formed, a deeper truth clawed at the edges of his fading awareness. He saw himself as others saw him: caustic, demanding, impossible to please. He’d assembled his team not as collaborators but as subjects, expecting them to bow to his intellect while contributing nothing but criticism and contempt.</p> <p>His heart stuttered, then stopped. Blood ceased its ancient journey through his veins. For all intents and purposes, he was dead—a corpse propped up in a gaming chair, surrounded by the detritus of wasted days.</p> <p>In this temporary death, visions danced behind his closed lids. He saw himself as he could be: <span style="color:green">focused</span>, <span style="color:green">driven</span>, <span style="color:green">collaborative</span>. He saw the projects he might complete, the relationships he might build, the man he might become if he could break free from this chemical sarcophagus. But even in death, the visions felt distant, belonging to some other version of himself—a stranger wearing his face.</p> <hr/> <p>Minutes passed. Or perhaps hours. Time moved differently in death’s embrace.</p> <p>Then, as suddenly as it had left, life came rushing back. His heart jolted into rhythm with violent, desperate beats. Blood surged through awakening vessels, carrying oxygen to a brain starved of purpose. His eyes snapped open, and the familiar room crashed back into focus—unchanged, unforgiving, waiting.</p> <p>He was alive again, but the world remained exactly as he’d left it. The empty containers still littered his desk. The assignments still sat unfinished in his laptop’s folders. The silence still pressed against the walls where human connection should have been.</p> <p>The boy reached for another vial with trembling fingers, already planning his next temporary death. Outside, dawn was breaking over the campus, painting the sky in shades of possibility he could no longer see. <strong>Somewhere beyond these walls, his former teammates were probably awake, working on projects he’d abandoned, building futures he’d convinced himself they didn’t deserve.</strong></p> <p>But here, in this tomb of his own making, he prepared to die again rather than face the terrifying prospect of truly living.</p> <p>The glass vial caught the morning light, holding promises as empty as the life he was choosing to leave behind, one temporary death at a time.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="chapter-0-the-near-death-experience">Chapter 0: The Near Death Experience</h1> <p>The alarm’s shrill cry pierced through the fog of another restless night. 6:30 AM. His phone buzzed against the nightstand, vibrating with the urgency of a world that demanded his participation. He groaned, rolling over in sheets that hadn’t been changed in weeks, his body protesting every movement.</p> <p><em>Just five more minutes,</em> he thought, but his bladder had other plans.</p> <p>Stumbling out of bed, he shuffled toward the bathroom, feet catching on discarded clothes and empty energy drink cans. The fluorescent light flickered to life, casting harsh shadows across his gaunt reflection in the mirror. Dark circles ringed his eyes like bruises, testament to another night that had stretched until dawn.</p> <hr/> <p>Then it hit him.</p> <p>The sensation crashed over him like a tsunami of pure terror. His head felt like it was about to explode from the inside out, pressure building behind his eyes until the world began to blur and shift. Colors bled together, edges softened, and the familiar bathroom tiles became an abstract painting of nausea and fear.</p> <p>He stumbled, his shoulder slamming into the cold bathroom wall. His vision went completely white, then black, then white again—a strobe light of approaching unconsciousness. His heart hammered against his ribs with such violence that he could hear each individual beat echoing in his ears like gunshots in a cathedral.</p> <p><em><span style="color:red">Thump. Thump. THUMP.</span></em></p> <p>Cold sweat erupted across his skin, soaking through his shirt in seconds. He slid down the wall, legs giving out beneath him, and found himself sitting on the bathroom floor, gasping like a fish pulled from water.</p> <p><em><span style="color:red">This is it,</span></em> he thought with crystalline clarity. <em><span style="color:red">This is how I die. <b>Twenty years old, alone in a bathroom at dawn</b>, with nothing to show for it.</span></em></p> <p>The realization hit harder than the physical symptoms. All those dreams he’d abandoned like outdated assignments—escaping this suffocating country, building a life worth living, becoming the scientist he’d once imagined himself to be. They flashed before his eyes not as inspirations but as accusations, ghosts of futures he’d murdered with his own hands.</p> <p>Was this a heart attack? His mind raced through medical terminology absorbed from late-night internet spirals. Myocardial infarction. Cerebral hypoxia. Stroke. Hypertensive crisis. The words felt foreign and terrifying, clinical descriptions of his body’s rebellion against the abuse he’d inflicted upon it.</p> <p><em><span style="color:red">Twenty years old,</span></em> he thought again, the number feeling both impossibly young and devastatingly old. <em><span style="color:red">Twenty years old and dying in a bathroom because I couldn’t stop poisoning myself with stimulants and synthetic deaths.</span></em></p> <p>In that moment of pure terror, stripped of all pretense and ego, he saw his life with brutal honesty. The late nights weren’t productive—they were destructive. The games weren’t entertainment—they were escape from a reality he was too afraid to confront. The isolation wasn’t noble solitude—it was the natural consequence of driving away anyone who might have cared.</p> <p>If he survived this—<em>if</em>—things would change. They had to change.</p> <p><em><span style="color:green">I’ll sleep early,</span></em> he promised to whatever god or force might be listening. <em><span style="color:green">No more-anything until dawn. I’ll do something that matters, something that helps people instead of just feeding my own emptiness.</span></em></p> <p>The promises felt fragile and desperate, like prayers whispered in a foxhole. But they were real, carved into his consciousness by the sharp edge of mortality.</p> <hr/> <p>Gradually, the symptoms began to subside. His vision cleared. His heart rate slowed from a sprint to a jog. The crushing pressure in his skull eased to a dull throb. He remained on the bathroom floor for several more minutes, afraid to move, afraid to trust that the crisis had passed.</p> <p>When he finally stood, legs shaking, he caught sight of his reflection again. The same gaunt face, the same hollow eyes—but something had changed. Behind the exhaustion and fear, there was a flicker of something he hadn’t seen in months.</p> <p><strong><span style="color:yellow">Determination.</span></strong></p> <p>Or maybe just terror dressed up as resolve. Either way, it was more than he’d felt in a very long time.</p> <p>He splashed cold water on his face, watching the pale, frightened stranger in the mirror mimic his movements. Today would be different. It had to be.</p> <p>The question was whether the memory of this moment would survive the comfortable numbness of another temporary death, or whether it would fade like all his other promises to himself, lost in the endless scroll of digital oblivion.</p> <p>Only time would tell if he was strong enough to choose life over the seductive embrace of artificial death.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My depressed experience.]]></summary></entry></feed>