<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sabertoaster.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://sabertoaster.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-06-13T16:18:10+00:00</updated><id>https://sabertoaster.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Downfall don’t fall down.</title><link href="https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2025/downfall/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Downfall don’t fall down."/><published>2025-01-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2025/downfall</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2025/downfall/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="preamble">Preamble</h1> <p>The dormitory room reeked of stale air and neglect. Empty takeout containers formed a graveyard across his desk, their contents fossilized into unrecognizable shapes that caught the mild glow of his laptop screen. The boy—twenty but wearing the face of someone much older—sat hunched over his keyboard, fingers dancing across keys with the practiced precision of an addict feeding his habit.</p> <p>2:47 AM. The numbers burned red in the corner of his vision, but time had lost all meaning hours ago. Outside his window, the campus lay dormant, but inside this cramped sanctuary, he was wide awake, pupils dilated from the synthetic euphoria coursing through his veins.</p> <p>The small glass vial sat empty beside his mouse pad, its contents already absorbed into his bloodstream. <strong>Mortis</strong>, they called it on the forums. The temporary death. The ultimate escape from consciousness, from responsibility, from the gnawing awareness of his own mediocrity.</p> <hr/> <p>His roommate had moved out three weeks ago—something about “toxic energy” and “impossible to live with.” Good riddance. Now he had the entire space to himself, free to indulge without judgment, without interruption.</p> <p>The familiar warmth began spreading through his chest, that telltale sign that the Mortis was taking hold. His heartbeat slowed to a hypnotic rhythm, each pulse echoing in his ears like a countdown. The screen before him blurred, the endless scroll of content becoming a meaningless river of light and shadow.</p> <p><em><span style="color:red">“You’re better than this,”</span></em> he whispered to himself, the words tasting like ash. It was a lie he’d stopped believing months ago, but the ritual persisted—a final prayer before the chemical crucifixion.</p> <p>His breathing grew shallow. The euphoria hit like a tidal wave, washing away every sharp edge of reality. The disappointment from his failed group project, the humiliation of being cast out by people he’d thought were friends, the crushing weight of unrealized potential—all of it dissolved in the chemical bliss.</p> <p><em><span style="color:red">They didn’t deserve me anyway,</span></em> he thought as consciousness began to ebb. <em><span style="color:red">Unambitious. Weak. They couldn’t handle someone with real vision.</span></em></p> <p>But even as the lie formed, a deeper truth clawed at the edges of his fading awareness. He saw himself as others saw him: caustic, demanding, impossible to please. He’d assembled his team not as collaborators but as subjects, expecting them to bow to his intellect while contributing nothing but criticism and contempt.</p> <p>His heart stuttered, then stopped. Blood ceased its ancient journey through his veins. For all intents and purposes, he was dead—a corpse propped up in a gaming chair, surrounded by the detritus of wasted days.</p> <p>In this temporary death, visions danced behind his closed lids. He saw himself as he could be: <span style="color:green">focused</span>, <span style="color:green">driven</span>, <span style="color:green">collaborative</span>. He saw the projects he might complete, the relationships he might build, the man he might become if he could break free from this chemical sarcophagus. But even in death, the visions felt distant, belonging to some other version of himself—a stranger wearing his face.</p> <hr/> <p>Minutes passed. Or perhaps hours. Time moved differently in death’s embrace.</p> <p>Then, as suddenly as it had left, life came rushing back. His heart jolted into rhythm with violent, desperate beats. Blood surged through awakening vessels, carrying oxygen to a brain starved of purpose. His eyes snapped open, and the familiar room crashed back into focus—unchanged, unforgiving, waiting.</p> <p>He was alive again, but the world remained exactly as he’d left it. The empty containers still littered his desk. The assignments still sat unfinished in his laptop’s folders. The silence still pressed against the walls where human connection should have been.</p> <p>The boy reached for another vial with trembling fingers, already planning his next temporary death. Outside, dawn was breaking over the campus, painting the sky in shades of possibility he could no longer see. <strong>Somewhere beyond these walls, his former teammates were probably awake, working on projects he’d abandoned, building futures he’d convinced himself they didn’t deserve.</strong></p> <p>But here, in this tomb of his own making, he prepared to die again rather than face the terrifying prospect of truly living.</p> <p>The glass vial caught the morning light, holding promises as empty as the life he was choosing to leave behind, one temporary death at a time.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="chapter-0-the-near-death-experience">Chapter 0: The Near Death Experience</h1> <p>The alarm’s shrill cry pierced through the fog of another restless night. 6:30 AM. His phone buzzed against the nightstand, vibrating with the urgency of a world that demanded his participation. He groaned, rolling over in sheets that hadn’t been changed in weeks, his body protesting every movement.</p> <p><em>Just five more minutes,</em> he thought, but his bladder had other plans.</p> <p>Stumbling out of bed, he shuffled toward the bathroom, feet catching on discarded clothes and empty energy drink cans. The fluorescent light flickered to life, casting harsh shadows across his gaunt reflection in the mirror. Dark circles ringed his eyes like bruises, testament to another night that had stretched until dawn.</p> <hr/> <p>Then it hit him.</p> <p>The sensation crashed over him like a tsunami of pure terror. His head felt like it was about to explode from the inside out, pressure building behind his eyes until the world began to blur and shift. Colors bled together, edges softened, and the familiar bathroom tiles became an abstract painting of nausea and fear.</p> <p>He stumbled, his shoulder slamming into the cold bathroom wall. His vision went completely white, then black, then white again—a strobe light of approaching unconsciousness. His heart hammered against his ribs with such violence that he could hear each individual beat echoing in his ears like gunshots in a cathedral.</p> <p><em><span style="color:red">Thump. Thump. THUMP.</span></em></p> <p>Cold sweat erupted across his skin, soaking through his shirt in seconds. He slid down the wall, legs giving out beneath him, and found himself sitting on the bathroom floor, gasping like a fish pulled from water.</p> <p><em><span style="color:red">This is it,</span></em> he thought with crystalline clarity. <em><span style="color:red">This is how I die. <b>Twenty years old, alone in a bathroom at dawn</b>, with nothing to show for it.</span></em></p> <p>The realization hit harder than the physical symptoms. All those dreams he’d abandoned like outdated assignments—escaping this suffocating country, building a life worth living, becoming the scientist he’d once imagined himself to be. They flashed before his eyes not as inspirations but as accusations, ghosts of futures he’d murdered with his own hands.</p> <p>Was this a heart attack? His mind raced through medical terminology absorbed from late-night internet spirals. Myocardial infarction. Cerebral hypoxia. Stroke. Hypertensive crisis. The words felt foreign and terrifying, clinical descriptions of his body’s rebellion against the abuse he’d inflicted upon it.</p> <p><em><span style="color:red">Twenty years old,</span></em> he thought again, the number feeling both impossibly young and devastatingly old. <em><span style="color:red">Twenty years old and dying in a bathroom because I couldn’t stop poisoning myself with stimulants and synthetic deaths.</span></em></p> <p>In that moment of pure terror, stripped of all pretense and ego, he saw his life with brutal honesty. The late nights weren’t productive—they were destructive. The games weren’t entertainment—they were escape from a reality he was too afraid to confront. The isolation wasn’t noble solitude—it was the natural consequence of driving away anyone who might have cared.</p> <p>If he survived this—<em>if</em>—things would change. They had to change.</p> <p><em><span style="color:green">I’ll sleep early,</span></em> he promised to whatever god or force might be listening. <em><span style="color:green">No more-anything until dawn. I’ll do something that matters, something that helps people instead of just feeding my own emptiness.</span></em></p> <p>The promises felt fragile and desperate, like prayers whispered in a foxhole. But they were real, carved into his consciousness by the sharp edge of mortality.</p> <hr/> <p>Gradually, the symptoms began to subside. His vision cleared. His heart rate slowed from a sprint to a jog. The crushing pressure in his skull eased to a dull throb. He remained on the bathroom floor for several more minutes, afraid to move, afraid to trust that the crisis had passed.</p> <p>When he finally stood, legs shaking, he caught sight of his reflection again. The same gaunt face, the same hollow eyes—but something had changed. Behind the exhaustion and fear, there was a flicker of something he hadn’t seen in months.</p> <p><strong><span style="color:yellow">Determination.</span></strong></p> <p>Or maybe just terror dressed up as resolve. Either way, it was more than he’d felt in a very long time.</p> <p>He splashed cold water on his face, watching the pale, frightened stranger in the mirror mimic his movements. Today would be different. It had to be.</p> <p>The question was whether the memory of this moment would survive the comfortable numbness of another temporary death, or whether it would fade like all his other promises to himself, lost in the endless scroll of digital oblivion.</p> <p>Only time would tell if he was strong enough to choose life over the seductive embrace of artificial death.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My worldbuilding experience.]]></summary></entry></feed>