<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sabertoaster.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://sabertoaster.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-03-11T17:28:09+00:00</updated><id>https://sabertoaster.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">STIC - Generative AI for LLMs - An Experience</title><link href="https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2024/STIC-genai-for-llms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="STIC - Generative AI for LLMs - An Experience"/><published>2024-07-31T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-31T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2024/STIC-genai-for-llms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2024/STIC-genai-for-llms/"><![CDATA[<div class="row justify-content-center mt-3"> <div class="col-lg-8 col-md-10 mx-auto text-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/2024/genai-llm-banner-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/2024/genai-llm-banner-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/2024/genai-llm-banner-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/2024/genai-llm-banner.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="500px" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>So here’s the deal - instead of dragging myself to university for another dull summer quarter, I decided to play it cool and dive into something I actually give a damn about: AI courses. Yeah, I’m that ComSci major who’s way too into AI (no regrets though). One of these courses is this Generative AI for LLMs thing, offered through STIC - some program sponsored by organizations I honestly don’t know much about, but hey, free Coursera credits? I’ll take it!</p> <p>Since I just started this blog and don’t have time to make it fancy, I’m keeping it real and straightforward. Currently grinding through week 2 and hoping to blast through this course ASAP. Let me share what’s been cooking in my brain…</p> <h2 id="week-2-the-fine-tuning-saga">Week 2: The Fine-tuning Saga</h2> <p>First up, let’s talk about fine-tuning these massive language models. Here’s what I’ve learned (and actually managed to understand):</p> <ul> <li>Apparently, everyone’s obsessed with this thing called “few shot prompting” and fine-tuning. Cool stuff, not gonna lie.</li> <li>But here’s the kicker - if you try to fine-tune the whole model, it gets amnesia (they call it “CATASTROPHIC FORGETTING”) and forgets how to do other stuff. Not cool.</li> <li>The fix? You gotta train it on everything again with tons of samples. They call it “Multi-task instruction training” because apparently, everything needs a fancy name.</li> <li>Then there’s all this evaluation stuff about making sure the model acts “human-like” (whatever that means…)</li> <li>Oh, and benchmarks! Finally something I vibe with. BLEU, HELM, ROUGE (sounds like a makeup palette but okay) - these bad boys help us figure out if our model’s any good.</li> </ul> <h2 id="peft-because-nobodys-got-time-or-memory-for-full-fine-tuning">PEFT: Because Nobody’s Got Time (or Memory) for Full Fine-tuning</h2> <div class="row justify-content-center mt-3"> <div class="col-lg-8 col-md-10 mx-auto text-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/2024/peft-layers-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/2024/peft-layers-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/2024/peft-layers-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/2024/peft-layers.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="500px" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Fig 1. Layers doing their thing in PEFT (look at them layers, beautiful aren't they?) </div> <p>Let me drop some knowledge about model weights - it’s not just the weights you gotta worry about. You’ve got:</p> <ul> <li>Gradients</li> <li>Optimizer States (adam, stochastic, and all that jazz)</li> <li>Forward Activations (ReLU, sigmoid - the usual suspects)</li> <li>And a ton of temporary memory (like, 12-20x more than the actual weights. Yikes.)</li> </ul> <p>Why PEFT’s actually dope:</p> <ul> <li>Instead of messing with the whole model, you just tweak a few layers</li> <li>Usually just the last ones, ‘cause why fix what ain’t broken, right?</li> </ul> <h3 id="the-peft-toolkit">The PEFT Toolkit</h3> <ol> <li><strong>LoRA (Low Rank Adaptation)</strong> <ul> <li><strong>Create</strong> two rank decomposition matrices (fancy math stuff)</li> <li><strong>Train</strong> those bad boys</li> <li><strong>Multiply</strong> the hell out of them during inference</li> <li><strong>Broadcast</strong> the results to the original weight</li> </ul> <p>And boom! Your model’s suddenly better at whatever you’re trying to make it do.</p> </li> <li><strong>Prompt Tuning (aka The Mystery Box)</strong> <ul> <li>Something about “soft prompts”</li> <li>Honestly? I need to do more homework on this one ‘cause I don’t understand sh-</li> </ul> </li> </ol> <h2 id="week-3-rlhf-really-having-fun-with-this-stuff">Week 3: RLHF (Really Having Fun with this stuff)</h2> <div class="row justify-content-center mt-3"> <div class="col-lg-8 col-md-10 mx-auto text-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/2024/rl-diagram-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/2024/rl-diagram-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/2024/rl-diagram-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/2024/rl-diagram.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="500px" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Fig 2. The whole RL circus in one neat diagram </div> <p>Alright, let’s dive into this rabbit hole called Reinforcement Learning. Picture this: you’ve got this agent (think of it as a digital student) trying to figure out what’s what in its environment. It tweaks its behavior based on rewards, kind of like training a puppy, but with more math and less treats.</p> <p>Then comes RLHF - Reinforcement Learning with Human Feedback (or Really Having Fun, if you know what I’m sayin’). This is where it gets interesting:</p> <ul> <li>Helps stop the model from being a jerk (no racist stuff, harmful speech, or useless rambling)</li> <li>Uses actual humans to rate the model’s responses (expensive AF and takes forever)</li> <li>That’s why we need a Reward Model (trained with Supervised Learning to predict what humans would like)</li> </ul> <p>We also use this thing called Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO), but I’m not even gonna try explaining that one. If you’re curious, <a href="https://www.coursera.org/lecture/generative-ai-with-llms/optional-video-proximal-policy-optimization-1iZJO">check it out yourself</a> - good luck!</p> <h2 id="the-fine-print">The Fine Print</h2> <p>Look, there’s way more stuff in <a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/generative-ai-with-llms">this course</a> that I haven’t covered (or fully understood, let’s be real). If you’re into this kind of thing, go check it out yourself. Maybe you’ll get more out of it than my casual observations!</p> <p><em>PS: Stay tuned for more adventures in AI land - next time I might actually show some code. Maybe. If I’m feeling generous.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ai-ml"/><category term="artificial-intelligence"/><category term="machine-learning"/><category term="llm"/><category term="course-notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My journey diving deep into the world of LLMs - expect some casual thoughts, honest reactions, and maybe a few curse words]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with TikZJax</title><link href="https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2023/tikzjax/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with TikZJax"/><published>2023-12-12T22:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-12T22:25:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2023/tikzjax</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sabertoaster.github.io/blog/2023/tikzjax/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with TikZ code. TikZJax converts script tags (containing TikZ code) into SVGs.</p> <script type="text/tikz">
\begin{tikzpicture}
    \draw[red,fill=black!60!red] (0,0) circle [radius=1.5];
    \draw[green,fill=black!60!green] (0,0) circle [x radius=1.5cm, y radius=10mm];
    \draw[blue,fill=black!60!blue] (0,0) circle [x radius=1cm, y radius=5mm, rotate=30];
\end{tikzpicture}
</script>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="diagrams"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included TikZ code could look like]]></summary></entry></feed>